Mss.530.1.Ar2.1 Mss.530.1.Ar2.1
American Philosophical Society
Sir Charles Galton Darwin papers, 1911-ca. 1938
1911 - Circa 1938
Mss.530.1.Ar2.1
American Philosophical Society
40.0 Item(s)
This collection includes numerous Darwin writings, in manuscript and typescript, as well as letters to him from Niels Bohr, Max Born, M. Frenkel, Oskar Klein, J. E. Littlewood, H. Moseley, H. R. Robinson. The writings include such topics as magnetic storms, atom mechanics, and wave theory. There is also a copy of a paper in Darwin's hand by Henri Poincaré, "On the theory of Quanta" (published in Journal de Physique, 1912).
40 items.
Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift from Lady Katharine Pember and accessioned, 09/--/1963 (1963 1964ms, 1546ms).
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is also available on microfilm (Archive for the History of Quantum Physics, Reel 36).
General note
This collection was indexed and filmed for the Archive for the History of Quantum Physics, as described in Thomas S. Kuhn, et al., "Sources for the History of Quantum Physics: An Inventory Report" (Philadelphia, 1967).
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Galton Darwin was a British physicist.
Bohr, Niels Henrik David, 1885-1962; Born, Max, 1882-1970; Frenkel, Yakov Il'ich, 1894-1952; Klein, Oskar, 1894-1977; Littlewood, John E., (John Edensor), 1885-1977; Moseley, H. G. J., (Henry Gwyn Jeffreys), 1887-1915; Poincaré, Henri, 1854-1912; Robinson, H. Russell; Atomic orbitals.; Magnetic storms.; Physics.; Quantum theory.; Wave mechanics.
- Papers
  - Notes on Symmetry groups, [1914]; 11-1/2x9, 10-1/2x8; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    Scope and Contents note
    A.D. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics No.1.)
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, Jan. 17, [1914]; 6x3-3/4; Moseley, H. G. J. (Henry Gwyn Jeffreys), 1887-1915
    Oxford, Eng., A.L.S. 12p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) His experiments on the spectrum and comments on electromagnetic theory.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, Feb. 1, [1914]; 6x3-3/4; Moseley, H. G. J. (Henry Gwyn Jeffreys), 1887-1915
    Oxford, Eng., A.L.S.with initials. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics, No.1.) Says that his formula is emerging triumphant and comments on atomic properties.
  - Graph, relating to "Collisions of Alpha particles with hydrogen nuclei,", [1921]; 8-3/4x5-1/2; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    Phil. Mag., vol. 41; D. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, June 15, [1921]; 11-1/2x8-1/2; Littlewood, John E. (John Edensor), 1885-1977
    Isle of Wight,. A.L.S. 7p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No. 1.) Forwards notes on his problem. Physics.
  - On a theory of the cause of magnetic storms [Smith prize essay], Jan., 1911; 11-1/2x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D.S. 30p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1)
  - On the theory of Quanta, 1912; 11-1/2x9; Poincarèè, Henri, 1854-1912 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D.in the hand of Sir Charles Galton Darwin. 29p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Taken from the Journal de Physique. Ser.V.vol.II,1912,pp.5ff.
  - The theory of radiation, Aug., 1912; 10-1/2x8; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    Typed D. 55p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Notes on atom mechanics, 1919; 11-1/2x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D. 46p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Critique of the foundations of physics, July, 1919; 11-1/x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D. 6p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, June, 1921; 7x4-1/2; Littlewood, John E. (John Edensor), 1885-1977
    A.L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) States that he made certain changes in a particular letter. For letter in question, see:Littlewood. to Darwin; June 15, 1921.
  - The Wave Theory and the Quantum Theory, 1923; 11x8-1/2; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    [?] Typed D.S.with penciled signature. 8p. (See Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Printed: Nature, vol.111,[1923] 771-773
  - The Quantum Postulate and the Recent Development of Atomic Theory, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962
    Typed D. 12p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Enclosed originally in letter from Bohr to Darwin; Oct. 16, 1927.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, March 16, 1927; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Frenkel, M
    Leningrad, A.L.S. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.1.) Thanks for his publications, and he did not know of them. Problems in physics.
  - M[ax] Born to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, 1927 April 7; Born, Max, 1882-1970
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, Oct. 4, 1927; 11x8-3/4; Schrödinger, Erwin, 1887-1961
    Zürich, A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Approves of his work on the spinning electron. Physics.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton) Darwin, Oct. 16, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962
    Copenhagen, A.L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Returns his paper and comments on it. Forwards paper of his own on the quantum theory. For paper,see; Bohr. Quantum Postulate...[1927].
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, Oct. 22, 1927; 11x8-1/4; Schrödinger, Erwin, 1887-1961
    A.L.S. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No. 1.) Presents his argument for a proposition in physics.
  - Letter to [Sir Charles Galton] Darwin, Nov. 23, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Klein, Oskar
    Copenhaven, Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archiv for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Comments on his paper and states that he and Bohr have discussed it.
  - Letter to [Sir] Charles [Galton Darwin], Dec. 6, 1927; 10-1/4x8-1/4; Robinson, Harold Roper
    Cardiff, Wales, A.L.S.with initials. 5p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Comments on his ideas on vector waves and personal problems. Friendly letter.
  - Wave equations, Nov. 19, 1928; 11-1/2x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Letter to [Arthur Stanley] Eddington, 1931-2; 11-1/2x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    ca.. A.L. 13p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Concerning wave mechanics.
  - Evaluation of Dispersion Formulae by methods like Schrödinger's. There is nothing original, only it is rather too complicated to work out anew every time, Jan., 1934; 11-1/4x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D. 28p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Letter to [Sir] Charles [Galton Darwin;?]., 1938; 9x5-3/4; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962
    A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.) Comments on European condition. Thanks for reprint on eugenics.
  - Papers on physics, July, 1963; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    1911-1934. D. ca.270p. Various sizes. (see Archive for the History of Quantum physics Presented by Lady Katharine Pember Darwin; These have been filmed on Film No. 36 of filming program for the Archive of the History of Quantum Physics.
  - Notes on "The Green Method for Electromagnetic Equations, etc.", Undated; 11-3/4x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    A.D. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)
  - Numerical values for Planck's radiation formula., Undated; 11-1/2x9; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962 (Drawer Oversize)
    A.D. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.1.)